它取名自罗马战神，
It takes its name from the Roman God of War,
夜空一颗遥远的暗红色的星球，
a distant, rusty orb in the night sky,
几百年来引起遐想的地方。
a source of rampant speculations for centuries.
是另一个文明的所在吗?
Could it be home to a rival civilization?
它的表面真的有张人脸吗?
Is there really a face on its surface?
这个迷人的行星邻居仍然迷惑着我们。
This intriguing planetary neighbor still captivates us.
即是未来殖民的潜在基地，
And as both a potential base for future colonization.
还保持着40亿年古老的生命秘密。
And the keeper of 4 billion year old biological secrets.
火星，红色的行星，
Mars, the red planet
可能掌握着我们未来和过去的关键。
may hold the keys to both our future and our past.
【历史频道】第Ⅰ02集·火星·红色行星
★★★★★ 字幕制作：五羊皮 ☆☆☆☆☆
E
S
R
E
V
I
N
U
History Channel·The Universe·Ⅰ02of14·Mars·The.Red.Planet
E
H
T
宙
宇
如果人类曾经在我们太阳系另一个地方居住过的话，
If human beings ever inhabited another world in our solar system,
这是最有可能的候选之地。
this is the most likely candidate.
红色行星，火星。
The red planet, Mars.
对一个地球来的访客，火星旅行
To a visitor from Earth, a tour of Mars
可能非常象让人想起家乡的地方。
might be very reminiscent of places back home.
象南加利福尼亚莫哈韦沙漠。
Places like Southern California's Mojavi Desert.
地理和天文生物学家肯恩·尼尔森，
Geo- and astro-biologist Ken Nealson,
发现这个沙漠如此象火星，
find this desert area, so much like Mars,
他来到这里试图更好地了解火星上的条件。
he comes here to try to better understand conditions on the red planet.
在着死亡之地周游，你会看到
You travel around here in the doom baggy and you'll see
火星上的死亡之地一样的面貌。
features that look just like the doom features on Mars.
如果你更深入的环顾周围，看到所有的这些红色的山丘，
If you go further and look in the background, and see all of this red hills,
满是氧化铁，就象在火星上看到的一样。
full of iron oxydes that we see on Mars.
火星堆满了铁，
Mars is filled with iron,
和氧化铁，基本上生了锈，化为了尘埃，
and its oxidized iron, basically rust, turns into dust particles
除了美丽的山丘外，还有红色的大气层，
and in addition to the beautiful dunes, you have this red atmosphere
有时行星的表面充满了红色。
sometime red all over the surface of the planet.
巨大的尘埃风暴。
Huge dust storms.
不是随随便便叫它为红色行星的。
They don't call it the red planet for nothing.
然而火星的地形与地球相仿，
But while much of the martian terrain is similair to Earth,
一些地理面貌完全就象
some geological features dwarf,
我们的地球上的某些特征。
any of there kind on our home planet,
一座山命名为Olympus Mons，拉丁文的奥林匹斯山。
a mountain named the Olympus Mons, latin for mount Olimpus,
是太阳系里所知的最高的山峰。
is the tallest known peak in the solar system.
是座著名的死火山，高耸在火星表面15英里。
It's a know dormed volcano, that rises fifteen miles above the martian surface.
假如你把奥林匹斯山的照片，
If you took a picture of Olympus mons,
和珠穆朗玛峰放在一起，和
an put it next to mount Everest, and
和夏威夷最大的岛，甚至把岛的海下部分一起拿上来，
and the big island of Hawaii, even taken all the way down to the base of the ocean,
比较火星上的奥林匹斯山，简直就是小不点了。
they look like molehills, compared with Olympus Mons on Mars.
那座山如此之大，你在它的斜坡上时，
That mount is so large you can be on its slopes
不会感觉是在火山的斜坡上，
and you would not know that you're on a slope of a volcano
在你登上山顶之前，这是因为它的基座实在是大。
because the based is so huge, before you get to its sommit.
然而，受启发的是火星表面看来
Yet, as inspiring as the martian surface appears,
对人类生存是个残酷荒凉之地。
it is a brutal, inhospitable zone for human beings.
绿色航行...
Green board...
五... 四... 三... 二... 一...
5... 4... 3... 2... 1...
点火，delta2号升空
Engine start and lift off of the delta 2 rocket
携带着精神号从地球飞向火星。
carrying the Spirit from Earth to planet Mars.
它是冰凉的，干燥的，荒凉的，
It's cold, it's dry, it's desolated,
有尘埃风暴，一次可以遮盖天空几个星期，甚至几个月。
there are dust storms, that can darken the skies for weeks, even months at a time.
在晚上温度下降到零下100度，
It goes down to a hundred degrees below zero
在每一个夜晚。
at night, every night.
配合这个寒冷的环境是没有氧气的大气层。
Compounding this cool conditions, is an atmosphere with no oxygen.
火星的空气和偶尔的云层
Martian air and even occasional clouds formations
几乎充满了二氧化碳。
are made up almost entirely of carbon dioxide.
所以他不是个好地方，如果你正好在那里，不会喜欢它的。
So it's not a nice place, you wouldn't enjoy it, if you're right there.
火星是地球的小的近亲。
Mars is small, relative to the Earth.
只有地球的一半大。
Only about half the size of our planet.
距离地球从没少于过3400万英里。
Its distance from us it's never less than 34 million miles.
它看起来只是天空上一颗小小的红色星球。
It appears as nothing more than a tiny red orb in our night sky.
尽管如此，几百年来，火星还是迷惑了人们。
Even so, Mars has captivated human kind for centuries.
它的名字取自罗马战神的名字。
The planet takes its name from the Roman God of war.
罗马人将战争和动荡和这个遥远的地方联系在一起，
The Romans associated this distant world with ostility and unrest,
是因为它那血一般的颜色，而且还因为它在天上与众不同的运动。
because of its blood-like colour, and because of its distinctive movement in the sky.
火星奇迹。它不会做其他星球做的事情。
Mars wonders. It doesn't do what the stars do.
红色星球有时会在天上向后移动。
The red planet occasionally appears to be moving backward across the sky.
其举止迷惑了观察者几百年。
A behavior that confounded observers for centuries.
然而在1514年，深入研究了这颗行星的运动后，
But in 1514, close study of this planetary movement,
顶尖的波兰天文学家哥白尼
lead Polish astronomer Nicholas Copernicus
革命性地定义了太阳系。
to a revolutionary understanding of the solar system.
在许多有记录的历史上，人们认为地球是宇宙的中心。
For much of recording history, people thought that Earth was at the center of the Universe,
接着来了哥白尼，他说道，
Along come Copernicus, and he says?
不，地球不可能是宇宙的中心。
No, maybe the Earth isn't at the center of the Universe.
物体围绕着太阳运行也许可以解释这一切。
Maybe the explanation for all this is that, things are going around the Sun.
如果行星围绕着太阳运行，那么我们能够解释为什么
And if all the planets are going around the Sun, then we can explain why
当地球越过在轨的火星时，
as Earth passes Mars in the orbit,
火星会往后倒退的原因。
Mars begins to wonder in our sky.
看上去往这边跑，接着就往那边跑。
Looks like it's going this way and then the source goes this way.
哥白尼通过一段时间的观察，
By the time of Copernicus'observations,
火星和地球相互在各自的轨道上运行，
Mars and the Earth had been passing each other and their respective orbit,
有45亿年了。
for some 4.5 billion years.
足够的时间让两颗行星发展成为两个非常不同的世界。
Time enough for the two planets to evolved into very different worlds.
一个温暖，潮湿，富含氧气。
One warm, wet and oxygen rich.
另一个则寒冷，干燥，没有氧气。
The other cold, dry and oxygen depleted.
但是现在相信，它们的差异并不完全如此。
Yet it's now believed that the differences weren't always so stark.
科学家现在认为火星曾经也很温暖，
Scientists today think that Mars was once warm enough
大量的水在其表面流淌。
for large amounts of liquid water to flow across its surface.
当我们观察现在的火星时，卫星的最佳图象
When we look at Mars today, in our best satellite images,
告诉了我们和第一次火星探测飞行看到的相同的信息，
they tell us the same message we heard from the first mission to Mars,
今天的火星上没有液态水，
and that there is no liquid water on the planet today
但无可争辩的事实是
but there's virtually incontrovertible evidence
火星上曾经有过水。
that there was water there in the past.
大家都知道，水流过任何一种土壤时，
Everybody knows that when water flows to any sort of dirt,
会有其特征的，
there are caratteristic structures,
水流淌过还有其他的作用，
there are other functions of that water running through,
而当看到卫星传回的火星的图象时，
and when we look at the pictures of Mars, of satellites images,
我们看到非常类似的构造
we see very similar structures
引导我们作出肯定的结论，
leading us to the absolute conclusion
火星曾经比现在温暖和湿润得多得多。
that Mars was once far warmer and wetter than it is now.
今天的火星当然是片荒漠之地，
Mars of course is a harsh desert today,
那么曾经发生了什么?
so what could have happened?
什么宇宙过程会给太阳第四颗行星
What cosmic process could have brought about such a dramatic transformation
带来如此戏剧性的变化呢?
of the fourth planet from the Sun.
故事还得从太阳系说起。
The story begins with the origin of the solar system.
45亿年前的某个地方，
Somewhere in the range of 4.5 billions years ago,
我们的太阳系从一个超新星里诞生了。
our solar system sprang from a supernova.
一个恒星的爆发喷发出
A stellar explosion emitting a swirling mass
粒子和气体的旋涡状物质。
of molecular particles and gasses.
这个旋涡状物质或"星云"开始冷却，
This swirling mass or "nebula" began to cool
而且，随着冷却开始聚集，并分开变成粒子环。
and, as it did, it condensed and separated into rings of particles.
这些粒子开始吸附或
These particles began to accrete or gradually
逐渐结合形成行星。
come together to form planets.
增长的过程产生了热，
The accretion process creates heat
较重的粒子下沉到物质团的中心。
and heavier particles sink to the center of the accumulating mass.
所以火星最终形成了一个熔化的铁核。
So Mars eventually formed a molten iron core.
这个熔核产生了一个强大的磁场。
This churning molten core generated a powerful magnetic field.
磁场环绕着火星，就象保护盾一样，
The field projected outwards surrounding Mars like a protective shield,
阻挡了来自太阳的有害射线。
blocking harmful emissions from the Sun.
来自太阳持续的压力我们称为太阳风。
You have this constant pressure from the Sun which we call the solar wind.
太阳由质量子，电子，宇宙射线组成，
The solar wind is made of protons, electrons, cosmic rays,
所有的带电粒子
all of these kinds of charged particles
会电离大气层，
that could ionize the atmosphere,
就象我们说的，把大气吹走。
as we call, sputter it away.
但是火星最终失去了它的保护盾
But eventually Mars lost its protective shield
和大部分的大气层。
and most of its atmosphere.
这个过程结束的时候，火星开始冷却。
The moment the accretion process ended the planet began to cool.
铁核不能再产生磁场，
The iron core was no longer able to generate this magnetic field
接着太阳风开始重击火星表面。
and then the solar wind started pounding the surface of Mars.
这是大多数人相信的假设。
That's a scenario that a lot of people believe.
大气层的丧失剥夺了火星的温暖和压力，
The loss of atmosphere stripped the martian surface of warmth and pressure
因为水需要温度和压力才能保持液态，
and since water needs both warmth and pressure to remain in liquid form,
在火星表面水无法保持稳定。
water is no longer stable on the martian surface.
如果把一盘水放在火星上，
If we put a pan of water out there on Mars it's gonna
会很快蒸发，同时也会结冰。
evaporate very fast and try to freeze at the same time.
不管是蒸发还是结冰，你都不会有液态的水了。
One or the other will win out, but you won't have a nice liquid pan of water.
不是说火星上一点没有水。
That's not to say however that there's no water on the planet at all.
虽然火星上不存在液态的水，
While liquid water is no longer stable on Mars,
但冰冻的水，冰，就是另一个故事了。
frozen water, ice, is a different story.
有证据证明直到今天
And evidence suggests that still today
大量的水结的冰可能就在火星极地下面。
tons of water ice might lie just below the martian polar caps.
锁定在那里的冰可能就是
Locked within that ice might just be
太空探险的圣杯。
the Holy Grail of space exploration.
可以通过地球上望远镜看到它的存在，
They're visible through simple telescopes on Earth
在经过太空接近火星时，
and they are inquestionably the first planetary features noticeable
这被清楚地表明为它的第一特征，
during an approach to Mars through space,
在火星的极地。
the martian polar caps.
神秘的白色冰雪世界，
Mysterious snowy white ice worlds,
覆盖在红色星球的顶部和底部。
sheathing the top and bottom of the red planet.
事实上我们叫做干冰的是二氧化碳，
Actually what we call dry ice is frozen carbon dioxide
大气层非常干燥，几乎都是二氧化碳，
the atmosphere is very thin and it's nearly all carbon dioxide,
所以在非常寒冷的情况下会结晶，
so when it gets very cold what condenses out
是二氧化碳的雪，二氧化碳的冰。
is carbon dioxide snow, carbon dioxide ice.
虽然白色的冰帽的确是火星多彩的特征，
But while the white caps are certainly a colorful planetary feature,
但不是二氧化碳自身的结晶体，
it's not the frozen concentrations of CO2 themselves
那是科学家最感兴趣的。
that are of most interest to scientists.
认为隐藏在极帽下的东西
It's what's thought to be hidden beneath the polar caps
具有重要的意义。
that could have massive significance.
潜伏在覆土下的，
Lurking just below the top soil,
可能是数百万吨的冰冻水。
may be millions of tons of frozen water.
隐藏的水的冰看上去
Water ice hidden from view
从极地向四面八方放射出去数百英里，
appears to radiate out hundreds of miles in all directions from the poles
让科学家认为那可能是过去海洋
and leading scientists think it could be the residue
的残留物。
of once vast oceans.
可能水现在冻结在地表下面的冻土层里，
Likely the water's now frozen, in a kind of permafrost beneath the surface,
但是火星不同的地方可能会有压力和温度
but maybe there are pressures and temperatures in various areas of Mars
融化冰，可能会
that have liquified the ice and created perhaps
产生液体的水。
aqua forms.
我们可以看到撞击产生的坑。是一颗小行星撞击火星形成的，
We can see craters in an impact. This up an asteroid that's hit Mars
溅起大量物质，
blown up a lot of stuff, it doesn't blow out
没有象在月亮上那样溅飞干燥的粉尘，产生闪光和碎石，
dry powder like on the Moon and make rays and rubble,
变成泥泞的泥浆。
it turns out kind of a muddy slurry of stuff.
所以结论是实际上撞击到了冰，
So the conclusion is that you're actually impacting into ice
就象加拿大北方的永冻层，冻土带土层。
like northern Canada permafrost layers, a tundra kind of stuff.
轨道太空船已经看到了很强的指标
Orbiting spacecrafts have picked up strong indicators
说明火星极地固态水的存在。
for the existence of water ice at the martian poles.
远距离的土壤测量已经发现高级别的氢。
Remote measurements of soil composition have detected high levels of hydrogen.
水当然是一份氧和两份氢组成的，
Water of course is one part oxygen and two parts hydrogen,
所以冰可能覆盖在那些区域的地表之下是无可辩驳的。
so the possibility of ice hiding below the surface in those areas is overwhelming.
而在火星极地有冰存在的明显证据，
But while strong evidence of ice at the martian poles may be relatively new
那里存在着水，会联想到一个世纪前普遍认为的
speculation that water existed there became common more than a century ago,
红色星球上也存在着智能生命，
and its implication that intelligent life could also exist on the red planet,
在地球上引起广泛的盼望，
elicited wide spread anxiety on Earth
特别是在20世纪前半个世纪。
for much of the first half of the twentieth century.
天文学家在1610年首次将望远镜指向火星。
Astronomers pointed the first telescope towards Mars in 1610.
随着望远镜技术的不断改进，
As spyglass technology steadily improved,
红色星球模糊的印象
a blurred image of the red planet
比过去任何时候更靠近地球观察员的眼睛。
drew ever closer to the eyes of earthly observers.
在1877年，望远镜能够放大远方行星的映象，
By 1877 telescopes could enlarge the image of the distant planet,
所以能够大致看清远方的东西。
so that it appeared roughly the size of a dime held at harm's length.
当然按现代标准算不得什么，
Certainly not impressive by modern standards,
但对米兰天文台台长来说已经足够了。
but it was enough for the director of the Milano observatory,
乔伐尼·齐亚巴雷利，
Giovanni Schiaparelli,
努力勾勒火星表面，对其地貌进行命名。
to attempt to sketch the martian surface and name its geological features.
齐亚巴雷利窥视那朦胧多变的映象，
Schiaparelli peered at the hazy shifty visage
几个月里一晚接着一晚。
night after night for months.
他看到了火星表面他认为的十字交叉线。
And he sees what he thinks are criss-cross lines on the surface of Mars.
后来证明，他看到的不完全是那里有什么，
It turns out later, what he saw isn't exactly
但是通过他那粗糙的望远镜还是能看到什么的。
what's up there, but still through his crude telescope that's what he could see.
尊敬的意大利天文学家勾画了这些线条
Respected italian astronomers sketched these lines
并给它们取了名字。
and gave them a name.
齐亚巴雷利认为那些线条象
Schiaparelli interpreted these lines as
某种河床，他并不真的了解。
channels of some sort, he didn't really know.
在这，他用意大利语称它们是"canali"，
Well, the italian word that he applied to them was "canali",
那个词，翻译成英语应该译成"河床"(channels)，
that word, translated to english should have been translated as "channels",
但是相反被误译成"运河"(canals)。
but instead it got mistranslated as "canals".
由于自然界没有看到过直线，
Since straight lines do not normally appear in nature,
齐亚巴雷利勾画的时候产生了念头
Schiaparelli sketches gave birth to the idea
即火星上应该存在智能生命的某种形态。
that some form of intelligent life must exist on Mars.
这是一个引人瞩目的想法，
It was an arresting notion,
天文学家一直为之广泛辩论。
widely debated among the astronomers of the day.
后来在1894年，
Later in 1894,
一个叫帕西瓦尔，罗威尔的波士顿富人
a wealthy Bostonian named Percival Lowell
竟然被这个想法吸引，
was so intrigued by this possibility
买了大望远镜安放在
that he paid to have a large telescope constructed on a mountain side
亚利桑那州旗杆市的山旁。
in Flagstaff, Arizona.
他化了接下来的20年对红色星球进行观察，
He spent the next two decades observing, sketching
勾画和推测。
and speculating about the red planet.
他自信已经看到火星上直线组成的网络，
He convinced himself that he was seeing networks of straight lines on Mars,
他认为那就是运河，
which he thought were canals,
在那些日子里和巴拿马运河一起成为大新闻，
what was the big news at the day with the Panama canal,
那是伟大的行星文明创造的，他们建造了运河。
that's what great planetary civilisations do, they build canals.
所以这是火星上从极地冰帽引水的运河，
So this was canals to bring the water down from the polar ice caps on Mars,
由于是寒冷，远离太阳，还是干燥，
which are cold and far from the Sun and dry,
所以他知道，所以他认为，
so he knew that and so he thought,
好了，在火星上他们必须为了生活运水。
well, they have to move the water to live on Mars.
那个想法正好刺激了每个人，火星上有个文明。
That idea just electrified everybody, that there was a civilisation on Mars.
在此背景下，1938年万圣节的晚上，
Against this backdrop on Halloween night 1938
一个名叫奥森·威尔斯的年轻播音员
A young actor named Orson Wells
推出了【世界大战】的广播剧。
broadcasted a dramatisazion of War of the Worlds
一部英国作家H. G. 威尔斯的小说，
A novella by british author H. G. Wells
描写险恶的火星人登陆地球，并进行肆虐。
In which sinister martians land on Earth and wreak havoc
我们把你带回Grovers磨房的卡尔·菲利普斯那里。
We now return you to Carl Phillips at Grovers Mill.
女士们，先生们，我在这里等一会儿，发生了一些情况
ladies and gentlemen, here I am wait a minute, something's happening
有一架飞机从那镜子弹出，跳在那路人的右边
There's a plane springing from that mirror and it leaps right at the advancing men
好家伙，他们变成了火焰!
Good Lord, they're turning into flame!
成千上万的市民认为这是真的入侵。
Thousands of citizens believed the invasion was real.
我对此深深地感到震惊和哀悼。
I'm deeply shocked and deeply regret for,
误会是短暂的。
The misunderstanding was short lived.
然而即便如此，广播只是给大众关于火星上
But even so the broadcast only served to fuel public speculation
可能存在智能生命的猜想添油加醋。
about potential intelligent life on Mars.
火星:吸引着人类数千年。
Mars: it has intrigued human kind for thousands of years.
20世纪中期，
And in mid 20th century
人类终于近距离地观察神秘的行星。
humans finally got a closer look at the mysterious planet.
1964年，美国航空航天局，NASA，
In 1964 the National Aeronautic and Space Admininstration, NASA,
向红色星球发射了小探险飞船。
launched the small exploration spacecraft toward the red planet
它的名字叫做水手4号，带有一个电视摄像机，
Its name was Mariner 4, it had a television camera
它的使命是飞过火星，传回图象。
and its mission was to fly past Mars and send back pictures.
它只能经过一次。
It could only make one pass.
科学家伴随着激动，
Scientists were filled with anxious excitement
充满了期待。
at the prospect of what they might see.
将会看到城市?将会看到运河?将会看到森林?
Well it is gonna see cities, is it gonna see canals, is it gonna see forests?
然而所有能看到的都是弹坑。
But all of what it saw it was craters.
飞船发回的图象只是非常模糊，弹坑看上去就象月亮上的一样。
It sent back pictures which just were very fuzzy and showed craters like on the moon.
这是一个巨大的失望。
It was a huge let down.
水手4号的图象显示了一个干燥多坑的沙漠的情景，
The Mariner 4 images revealed a dry cratered desert like
表面死寂的行星。
and seemingly dead planet.
有点象月亮，一点空气吹着周围的沙尘。
Sort of like the moon with a little air to blow the dust around.
但是探索火星的热情只是被降温。
But the enthusiasm for exploring Mars was only tempered.
6年后，在1971年，
And 6 years later, in 1971,
NASA向红色星球发射了另一艘飞船:水手9号。
NASA sent another spacecraft to the red planet: Mariner 9.
但是这时，舍弃了仅仅经过火星，
But this time, rather than just making a single pass by Mars
水手9号被制造成围绕火星几个星期，
Mariner 9 was engineered to orbit the planet for weeks
做一个完整的扫描。
and do a complete mapping.
努力得到了回报。
The effort paid off.
在等待了一个火星大范围的沙尘暴后，
After waiting out a planet wide dust storm,
水手9号开始发回壮观的图象。
Mariner 9 started returning spectacular images.
它发现了塔尔西斯高地，
It discovered the Tharsis bulge,
火星大肚皮的地方，靠近赤道。
The source of potbelly of the planet, near the equator.
它的隆起是由于集中了大规模的火山。
The bulge is a result of concentrated and massive volcanic activity.
塔尔西斯高地显示出来的特写，
The dominant feature of the Tharsis bulge
是最高的火山:奥林匹斯山。
is the monster volcano: Olympus mons.
奥林匹斯山的大小相当于密苏里州，如果把它放到美国中部，
Olympus mons is about the size of Missouri. If you put it in the middle of the US,
它将占据那张地图。
it would dominate that picture.
如果它重大爆发，火山的大小
If it had a major eruption, a volcano of that size
或许会吞没密苏里州的每一个地方。
would probably full up one state on every side of Missouri
所以，嗯，我的家乡在衣阿华州，将会被熔岩覆盖。
so, uh, my home town in Iowa would be under lava.
有趣的是，我们认为它是由三座火山组成的，
Interestingly it's composed of we think three separate volcanos
或至少以三种不同的方式喷发，如果你...
or at least it's erupted in three different ways, if you...
在它顶上飞过，你会看到三个分开的火山口。
fly over the top you see three separate calderas.
所以不仅仅是三倍大，而且还是地质上的怪物。
So it isn't just three times larger, this is a monster geological event.
事实上你站在它的边缘，它的斜坡是如此的平缓，
When infact if you're on the edge, the slope is so gradual
山顶在100英里以外，
and the peak is more than a hundred miles away
你不会知道那就是火山，它是巨大的。
and that you wouldn't know that it was a volcano. And it's that massive.
奥林匹斯山并不孤单。
And Olympus mons is not alone.
数百英里的东南向的山脉，
A few hundreds miles South-East of the mountains
三个其它的火山斜排成一列与庞大的火山保持着等距离。
stands a diagonal row of three other, evenly spaced enormous volcanos.
每一个都比地球上的同类大。
Each larger than any of its type on Earth.
然而，作为宏伟的，
Yet as magnificent as it is,
塔尔西斯地区并不是水手9号
The Tharsis region isn't the only spectacular
发现的唯一壮观的地址面貌。
geological feature discovered by Mariner 9.
在高地的东部边缘是个
At the Eastern edge of the bulge is a colossal
红色行星外壳上的巨大裂口。
tear in the crust of the red planet.
它被阵为"水手谷"，水手谷，
It's called "Valles Marineris", Mariner Valleys,
是水手9号给自己的荣誉。
in honour of the Mariner 9 orbiter itself.
你瞧这，它有美国这么宽。
You look at this thing, it's like the width of the United States.
它是劈开的峡谷。
It's this cleaved valley
你知道美国的大峡谷吗?
You know the Grand Canyon in the United States?
把它拿起来，放大胆，把它弄得象美国一样大小，
Pump it up, put it on steroids, make it the size of the United States itself
你就得到了水手谷。
and you got Mariner Valleys.
导致这巨大的裂口在火星表面的地质构造
The geological mechanism that causes this immense rupture in the martian surface
至今仍然是个谜，科学家只能进行猜测。
is yet a mistery. Scientists can only speculate.
我喜欢的一个构造
One mechanism which I like
在那个叫做塔尔西斯高地不远。
is that there's a place called Tharsis bulge not far away.
它是许多熔岩和其他东西堆积起来的，
And it's so much lava and other things have accumulated,
充满了熔岩并能把一个巨大的环放在火星表面。
that it's filled and could put a giant torque on the surface of Mars.
象拉链那样扯开。
And pulled this apart like a zip.
好啦，谁知道那是真实的...
Well, who knows if that's true...
需要一个不同于我们了解的任何事情的构造
but one needs a mechanism dfferent from many things we know
去解释它的存在.
to explain the existence of that.
由于水手9号的极其成功，
With the stunning success of Mariner 9
NASA下一个采取的步骤
the next logical step for NASA
是用太空船登陆火星表面。
was to land a spacecraft on the actual surface of Mars.
科学家渴望测试岩石和土壤样本，寻找生命的踪迹。
Scientists were eager to test rock and soil samples for sign of life.
1976年，海盗号到达火星，完成这个使命。
In 1976 the Viking mission reached the planet to do just that.
它有卫星和登陆平台组成，
It had both an orbiter and a landing component.
装备有机器人测试仪器。
equipped with robotic test instruments.
我们已经降落在地面上了，铲起土壤和...
And we get right down on the surface and scoop up some soil and...
没有发现什么，
we don't find a thing.
火星看上去象是个寒冷，干燥，荒漠之地。
Mars looks like a cold, dry, dead place.
不过虽然海盗登陆车在地下劳而无功，没造成轰动效应，
But while the Viking lander toiled the way underground failing to make headlines,
但是在火星高处，
high above the martian surface
海盗登陆车还是设法捕捉到了迷人的图象。
the Viking orbiter managed to capture a mystifying image.
在飞越火星名叫基多尼亚的区域时，
While flying over a region of Mars called Cydonia,
卫星拍摄到了一幅在交叉照亮下的地表造型。
the orbiter snapped an image of a land formation under cross lighting.
初一看造型象张人脸。
Startingly the formation resembled a human face.
作为一个笑话，NASA的科学家把图片作为新闻发表，
As a joke NASA scientists showed the photos to the press
说是他们在火星上发现的面孔。
remarking about the face they'd found on Mars.
在更加均匀的照明下，当然
Under more even lighting conditions, of course
那个火星地貌怎么看都不象一张脸，
the martian terrain feature doesn't look like a face at all
只是一群山丘。
Just a jumble of hills.
但在火星上的脸的故事到处流传时，
But in certain circles the story of the face on Mars
NASA坚持掩盖了几年。
and its NASA cover up persisted for several years.
其他方面的火星爱好者跟随海盗号
True Mars enthusiasts on the other hand face a more sober reality
面临着一个更加清醒的现实。
following the Viking mission.
随着海盗号探险传来的没有生物现象的确切证据，
With no definitive evidence of biology resulting from the Viking experiments,
对红色星球的兴趣平静了数年。
interest in returning to the red planed quieted for several years.
接着，在1984年，
Then, in 1984,
一位在南极远征的年轻科学家，
a young scientist on an expedition in Antarctica,
得到了注入新的活力的发现，
made a discovery that ultimately infused new energy
唤起了揭示火星上生命的希望。
and hope into the quest to uncover life on Mars.
在1984年12月，
In December 1984
NASA地质学家在南极收集陨石时，
NASA geologist, on a meteorite gathering expedition in Antarctica,
找到了一个古老的样本。
found an odd specimen.
陨石有着不一样的颜色。
A meteorite with an unusual colour.
有点绿色，
A sort of green hue.
大部分是灰色或褐色。
Most are grey or brown.
回到NASA在休斯敦的约翰逊太空中心，
Back at NASA's Johnsons space center in Houston,
那里储存着大量的石头，
where such rocks are stored,
它的编号是ALH84001。
it was labeled ALH84001.
不管它古老的颜色，
Despite its odd colour,
科学家设想它是小行星的碎片。
the scientists assumed that it was a piece of an asteroid.
所以石头被归类在陨石组，
So the rock was pigeonholed into a group of meteorites,
被放置了6或者8年。
and it stayed there for six or eight years.
错误的分类。
Misclassified.
接着在90年代初期，
Then, in the early 1990s,
一个分析员，研究小行星，
an analyst, researching asteroids,
拿起这片ALH84001，
placed a piece of ALH84001,
放到电子显微镜下，
under an electron microscope.
他很快意识到看到的不是块普通的陨石。
He soon realized that he was not looking at a normal meteorite.
看上去是块火星的碎片。
He was looking at a piece of Mars.
石头有着和1979年找到的火星陨石匹配的特征。
The rock had characteristics that matched another Martian meteorite found in 1979.
更多的科学家开始研究那个样本，
More scientist began studying that sample,
他们感到惊讶，
and they were astonished,
他们最后终于发现，
when they eventually found,
有看上去象碳球的东西。
what looked like carbon globules.
碳，至少在地球上，
Carbon, at least on Earth,
是构成生命的主要元素。
is the primary building block of life.
老资格的科学家大卫·麦凯，
Senior scientist David McKay,
领军研究小组。
headed up the research group.
我的想象被碳酸盐印证了。
My imagination was signated by the carbonates.
我说"嘿，这些碳酸盐真是个奇怪的天体。
And I said? "Hey, these carbonates are a really strange welkin.
它们从哪来?让我们来瞧一下。"
How do they form? Let's look at those?"
小组全力投入在岩石样本旁，
Closures groups near the rock sample,
但也带来了更纯正的发现。
brought even more sterling discoveries.
那些小珠里存在的化学成分，
The kind of chemistry that went on in those globules,
是与地球上的生命相关联的。
is associated with life on Earth.
至少在电子显微镜扫描图像里，
At least one, scanning electron microscope image,
显示出疑似存在有机物。
revealed the structure that looked suspiciously organic.
似乎象条虫子。
Almost like a worm.
会是原始的火星生物吗?
Could it be a trace of primitive Martian biology?
我认为那个虫子是...是...生物.
I think that worm is... Is... biologic.
不论细菌的化石有没有疑问，
Whether is a complete fossil of bacterium is problematical,
它可能是细菌的一部分，
it could be a part of that bacterium,
它可能是某种切片，
it could be a section of one,
但是它在我眼里是个生物。
but it's biologic in my view.
"欢迎各位，
"I'd like to welcome everybody here today.
这是个难忘的日子，
It's an unbelievable day.
今天对我来说是非常非常激动"。
It's very very exciting for me".
终于在1996年，在长达两年的研究后，
Finally in 1996, after more than two years of study,
在他们在其中建立了4个独立证据的情况下，
in which they have built four independent lines of evidence,
研究小组一切就绪。
the team was ready.
他们宣布了他们的假设。
They announced their hypothesis.
ALH84001包含了火星上可能存在生命的证据。
ALH84001 contain possible evidence of passed life on Mars.
"我们推定...
"We conclude that...
这是一个火星上的早期生命。"
This is evidence for early life on Mars".
NASA举行了一个大型的记者招待会，
NASA held a major press conference,
然而不是每个人都相信。
but not everyone was convinced.
全球的实验室都要求将岩石的样本
Labs across the globe requested samples of the rock
让他们自己做分析。
to conduct their own analysis.
最后，在经过几个月的激烈辩论后，
In the end, after months of at times acrimonius debate,
共识是...
the consensus was...
没有形成共识。
That there was no consensus.
发表的论文支持这个论点，
Papers were published in support of the claim
但是更多的则持反对意见。
but many more were published ebunking the idea.
"如果我们来看第一张幻灯片，
"If I could have the first slide please?
你看到的这个特写，
The features that you see,
可能是一些物体，例如，可能会..."
may be any number of things, for example, they could..."
许多研究员确信那是岩石的成分，
Many researchers are conviced that the formations in the rock,
那个似乎是火星生命的痕迹，
that appeared to be signs of Martian life,
实际上是由矿物活性造成的。
were actually caused by mineral activity.
多数人会说
The majority of people would say that
来自这个火星早期的陨石
there's no really biogenic activity
其实没有生物活动
from this meteorite from Mars.
开头那些推论是错误的。
Those initial hypothesis was incorrect.
我可以说在这一点上...
I would say at this point that...
作出的推论太天真了。
That's too simple hypothesis to take.
我不认为得到一个满意的结果，
I don't think the work is being completed to
研究就完成了。
a satisfactory end point.
也就是说不论怎样，
To say either way.
关于陨石的研究还在继续。
Work on the meteorite is continuing.
但即使研究员从未证实岩石存在火星生命的痕迹，
But even if researchers never confirmed that the rock contains signs of Martian life,
ALH84001有趣事件已经完全给寻找红色星球生命
the ALH84001 episode has already completely reinvigorated interest
注入了新的重要性。
in the quest for life on the red planet.
具有讽刺意义的是，寻找火星生命的新动力，
Ironically, the new push to find life on Mars,
往往引导科学家再次前往南极大陆。
has often led scientists yet again to the continent of Antarctica.
地球上这个地方的环境与火星上的环境相似。
Conditions, in this part of the world, are analogues in many ways to conditions on Mars.
寻找生命形态在这个极端环境下
Seeking out life forms that managed to thrive
形成繁衍，可能揭示
an extreme circumstances here, might shed light
原始生命曾经能否在红色星球上生存。
on how and where primitive life could have once taken hold on the red planet.
环境天体生物学家Dale Andersen关注的是
What environment astrobiologist, Dale Andersen, focuses on,
那个全年覆盖厚厚的冰的湖底。
is that the bottom of lakes, covered year-around, with thick layers of ice.
大多数人说是由于冰盖的作用吗?
Most people said that because of the ticks ice covers?
"你除了岩石以外，什么都不会发现。"
"You would find nothing but rocks?"
湖底没东西，希望非常渺茫。
There'll be very little to nothing on the bottom.
冰层封锁许多这样的湖泊，
The ice layer sealing off many of these lakes,
冰层厚达15英尺。
is up to 15 feet thick.
不过，要么炸开它，要么钻通它，
But rather than trying to blast or drill through it,
干扰下面的生态系统，
and disturbing the ecosystem below,
Andersen及其伙伴找到了大大减少破坏的办法。
Andersen and team have found a much less damaging approach.
他们用一大盘铜线圈制作一个通道。
They let a massive coil of copper tubing make an opening.
然后就用热的液体通过，
Then you just pass a hot liquid through it,
将它投在冰上，使冰融化降下去。
throw it down on the ice and it'll melt its way down.
用了24小时化开了冰，
It takes about 24 hours to melt through the ice
然后用这个漂亮的窟窿进行潜水。
and then makes this very nice clean hole to dive through.
潜水员身穿潜水服潜到水里。
Divers enter the water wearing full-body drysuits.
他们发现几乎每一个南极湖泊的湖底
And what they find at the bottom of nearly every Antarctical lake pad,
都是生命坚韧不拔的最好证据。
is a testament to the stubborn ternacity of life.
有机微生物丛
Mats of microbial organisms
在没有任何阳光的极度寒冷的环境下繁衍。
are thriving in frigid enviroments that receive virtually no sunlight.
大多数人会认为，在不足地表光线1%的地方，
Most people thought that, if you have less than about 1% of the surface light,
在那个湖底，不可能进行光合作用。
you won't have any photosynthesis taking place, down on the bottom.
没有足够的光，不会变老。
They won't be old to use enough light to live.
结果是光照水平下降到10%，到1%，它们还能进行光合作用。
It's turned out that they can photosynthesis with light levels down to 1/10 to 1%.
对安徒生和他的团队来说，
For Andersen and his team
原始的生物丛真是通往过去的一个窗口。
the pristine mats are truly a window to the past.
这里没有空调有机体，没有鱼类，没有昆虫，
There no air organism, no fish, no insects,
没有爬行动物，这些微生物种落
no animals creeping through it, so these microbial communities
不论动、植物再无干扰下，通过其自身依然有生长的机会。
have the opportunity to grow by themselves without interference, no matter animal or plants.
并让他们有机会以非常特殊的方式生长。
And that gives them the opportunity to grow in very special ways.
这可能微生物生命类似的形态
Is it possible that a similar form of microbial life
还会生存在火星恶劣的表面之下?
could still reside somewhere beneath the frozen surface of Mars?
特别是在氢含量高的极地?
Especially at the hydrogen-rich poles?
Andersen和科学家们希望是这样，相信这是值得研究的。
Andersen and scientists like it. Believe it is worth investigating.
倒计时，十..九..八..七..六..
T-Minus 10... 9... 8... 7... 6...
五... 四... 三... 二...
5... 4... 3... 2...
Delta2号带着火星探险机器人升空了。
And lifted off the Delta-2 rocket with the Mars exploration robot.
在2003年夏季，
In the Summer of 2003,
NASA的喷气推进实验室派出了两台探测飞船，
NASA's jet propulsion laboratory, delivered two exploration spacecrafts,
到火星的表面去。
to the surface of Mars.
到红色星球去进行每两年一次的会面，
Missions to the red planet are only feasible once every two years,
这是一次短暂的时间窗口。
during a specific short window of time.
发射必须准时，
The launch must be timed,
使飞船和火星在同一时间到达火星轨道的
so that the spacecraft and Mars arrive at a specific point in the planet's orbit
一个特定的点。
at the same time.
横跨3400万英里距离需要7个月。
The journey across the 34 million mile distance can take up to seven months.
轨道必须精确。
And the trajectory must be perfect.
需要精确到从地球到火星
The accuracy required to go from Earth to Mars
并击中火星上你想要的点，
and to hit the spot you want to be at on Mars
这相当于从洛杉矶投蓝进纽约的蓝筐。
is equivalent to shoot in a basketball from Los Angeles to New York.
并且通过时要不碰蓝框，不过没什么。
And have it go trough without hitting the rib. Nothing but that.
所有的系统已经输入了登陆的程序。
All systems are go for entering the step landing.
我们现在6分钟后开始，
We are currently 6 minutes from landing
在火星向阳面的古瑟夫坑登陆。
at the Gusev crater of solar hemisphere of Mars.
锁定每小时1.356英里。
Point lock at 1.356 miles per hour.
预计5秒钟后打开降落伞。
Expecting parachute deploy in 5 seconds.
探测到降落伞，
Parachute detected.
已经到达***********。
Expecting reach ***********.
太空船实际上成了漫游者。
The spacecrafts were actually rovers.
遥控车能够在火星表面行走
Robotic vehicles capable of travelling across the martian surface
并捅开包围物体。
and poking around.
漫游者是机器地质学家。
The rovers are robot geologist.
它们干的活是在火星上当我们的眼睛，我们的脚和手。
Their job is to be our eyes, our feet, our hands on the Martian surface.
我们通过它们探索火星。
We experience Mars through them.
它们能伸出去，能接触岩石。
They can reach out. They can touch rocks.
这是叫做Rat的装置。
There's this device called the Rat.
R.A.T.(岩石磨具)是一个钻石磨头的工具，
R.A.T. the Rock Abrasion Tool wich is a diamond-tip grinding tool that we can use
我们能够用来打孔进入岩石内部，
to grind into the interior of a rock,
所以我们实际上把它作为进入岩石的窗口。
and so we can actually get a window inside the rock.
它们有个装在机械臂末端的传感器，象个显微镜，
They have sensors on the end of that arm like there's a microscope,
来告诉我们它们看到的一切。
for telling us in detail what they look like.
所以我们有整套的工具，类似地质学家想要的，
So we've got a whole bunch of tools, similar to what the geologists would want,
如同他们亲临现场。
if they were actually phisically there on the scene.
漫游者被命名为精灵号和机会号，
The rovers were named Spirit and Opportunity
直到今天它们仍然在火星上探索，
and they are still exploring regions of Mars today,
在火星表面相互相距数百英里。
at locations on the planet hundreds of miles from eachother.
精灵号降落在古瑟夫坑。
Spirit landed in an area dubbed Gusev crater.
机会号相信是在干燥的湖床上。
The crater is believed to be a dried up lake bed.
所以如果水里曾经有过生物，
So if the water it once held contains biology,
精灵号会发现它的痕迹。
Spirit might uncover signs of it.
机会号降落在叫做梅里迪亚尼平原的区域。
Opportunity touched down in a region called Meridiani Planum.
这个区域很奇特，因为它含有一层赤铁矿，
The area is a triggy, because it contains an ancient layer of hematite
一层氧化铁，在地球上通常会含有水份。
an iron oxyd that on Earth usually formes in a spot that held liquid water.
到目前为止，两个漫游者都没有发现生命的痕迹。
So far neither rovers has found signs of life.
但是精灵号和机会号都发现了有价值的证据，
But both Spirit and Opportunity have uncovered helpful proof
即在火星表面曾经存在过大量的水。
that liquid water was once plentiful on the surface of the Red Planet.
我们看到了水地表下被水浸泡过的岩石，
We've seen places where water soaked the rocks beneath the surface,
看到了水曾在其表面流淌过的地方，在整个火星表面，
we've seen places where water came to surface and flowed, over the martian
制造了小小的波纹，仍然保存在岩石里
surface creating little ripples that are still preserved in the rocks
长达数十亿年。
billions of years later.
然而两个漫游者都没有靠近火星极地的冻土带
But neither rovers is close enough to the tundra-like martian Poles
去揭示实际冻结的水。
to uncover actual frozen H2O.
那是新的火星任务的第一目标，2007年夏季启程。
That is the primary goal of a new mission to Mars, launched in the summer of 2007.
这一使命称为凤凰，计划到固定的登陆点，
This mission is dubbed Phoenix, and its plan is to place a stationary lander
在火星的北极。
in the reaching of the martian North Pole.
登陆车有个强劲的机械臂，装有一个铲子。
The lander has a sturdy robotic arm, equipped with a scoop.
凤凰将挖掘极地的土壤。
Phoenix will excavate the polar soil.
亚利桑那大学的彼得·史密斯博士领导这个项目。
Doctor Peter Smith of the University of Arizona heads up the project.
我们完整的科学计划是关于
Our entire scientific mission is about
研究土壤的性质，以及冰对它的作用，
understanding the properties of the soil, and its inner action with the ice,
还有冰的性质和冰与空气的相互作用。
and the properties of the ice and the ice inner action with the atmosphere.
我们只有一个办法研究它，那就是靠我们的机械臂，
We have only one way to study it, and that's by using our robotic arm
这就是我们的回报，将会在那挖条小沟，
that's our back-o if you like. That's gonna dig a little trench,
取得土壤和期望的湿土的样本，如果能找到的话，
and provide samples of both soil and hopefully wet soil if we can find it,
还有冰，我们会分析那些样本，
and ice and we will analyze those samples
用我们太空船上的装置来分析。
with instruments on the deck of our spacecraft.
登陆车会从火星表面发回信号，
The lander will beam signals back from the martian surface
报告遥远的土壤和冰的分析结果。
reporting the result of the remote soil and ice analysis.
但在凤凰之前曾经在发射架上有过一次机会，
But before Phoenix has even had a chance to make it off the launch pad,
新的难题在传奇的"火星上的水"被揭示出来。
a new wrinkle in the saga of "Water on Mars" has revealed itself.
一直在红色星球轨道上运行的太空飞船发回的图象，
Images beamed back from a spacecraft currently orbiting the red planet,
显示了一个非常令人以外的事情。
show evidence of a very unexpected event.
看来在过去的一段时间里，流体曾经流淌过某些地方，
It appears that a liquid flow of some sort has accurred within the last few years,
一个小沟槽在火星深峡谷的边缘。
in a small gully at the edge of a deep martian ravine,
2001年，卫星发回了同一地方的照片，
In 2001 the orbiter took photos of the exact same spot,
然而看起来没有任何感兴趣的地方。
but nothing of interest showed up in those shots.
新照片另一方面显示出在沟壑里有白色的残留物。
The new photos on the other hand, showed a white residue in the gully.
残留物看起来象在水流的左后方，
A residue simingly left behind by a flow of liquid.
水可能从地面上流出，
possibly where water spurted from the ground
流过了几百码，
and flowed for several hundred yards,
然后蒸发掉了。
before transforming into vapor and vanishing.
科学家至今没有明白怎么会有这么个水流，
Scientists do not yet understand what might have caused such a flow,
许多人怀疑是来自内部的热，
but many suspect that it's a result of some form of internal heat
火星必然还保持着热量。
the planet must still contain.
毫无疑问，这是个有火山活动的平原，
Clearly, it's a plain that it's been vulcanically active,
我们所有的人都非常希望能在火星上一些地方找到含氢的物质。
and all of us are very hopefully that some places on Mars we could find hydro-thermovets.
我们不仅希望找到液态水，而且由于液态水暗示着
Not just beacause we want liquid water, but because liquid water implies that
将可以成为生命能发展和持续的环境。
this might be an environment that life could developed and be maintained.
这，当然全在于寻求生命。
It is, of course, all about the search for life.
所有说过和做过的
When all is said and done
惊人的科学之举，
the engine driving all of the astonishing scientific afford
去探索红色星球是人类不懈的追求，
to explore the red planet is the burning desire of human kind
在广袤的太空的其它地方或许存在着生命。
to know if life exists elsewhere in the vast reaches of space.
我想自从人类开化以来，
I think humans have, since the dawn of consciousness,
就想知道我们为什么会在这里，就会想知道那里有什么，
wondered why they're here and wondered what's up there
还想知道还会有其它的东西吗。
and wondered if there's more.
而..解答那些问题将会排进我们未来的日程，
And... answering that question will sort of put us in some kind of prospective
某种程度上会知道我们地球在宇宙的什么地方。
it'll tell us what our places in the universe, to some extent.
在火星上寻找生命也会帮助我们了解
Finding life on Mars could also help us understand the origins of life
在我们自己的星球上生命的起源。
on our own planet.
而且实际上会是火星与地球之间
And that could actually be in the case of Mars and Earth
重要的联系。
a significant connection.
火星上本身能产生生命并能很好地适应火星环境，
Mars developed life itself and maybe the conditions were right on Mars
但就不可能很好地适应地球环境。
but they weren't right on Earth.
然而火星传送生命给了地球。
And yet Mars seeded our planet.
也许通过陨石碰撞，火星的碎片抵达了地球。
Perhaps through meteoritic collisions, pieces of Mars arrived on Earth.
我们生命的细胞如今在这里繁衍，或许我们都曾经是火星人。
We're cells of life and that actually grew here. Maybe we could all be martians.
或者也许相反，你知道，或许生命在我们这个行星起源，
Or perhaps it was the reverse, you know, perhaps life originated on this planet,
然后移居火星。
and moved to Mars.
如果我们在火星上找到生命的证据，我们知道地球上有生命，当然，
If we find evidence for life on Mars and we know there's life on Earth, of course
接下来在所有的行星上就可能会有生命。
than there's probably life all over the place.
宇宙可能充满着生命.但如果不是，
The universe is probably teeming with life. And if it didn't,
那就会使我们多了一点点特别的感觉。
then it makes us feeling like we are a little bit more special.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing